<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[atoms4peas]]></title>
  <link href="http://ferenc-dv.github.io/atoms4peas/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ferenc-dv.github.io/atoms4peas/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-02T22:22:54-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://ferenc-dv.github.io/atoms4peas/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ferenc Dalnoki-Veress]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://ferenc-dv.github.io/atoms4peas/blog/2014/05/19/new-post/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-19T20:00:02-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ferenc-dv.github.io/atoms4peas/blog/2014/05/19/new-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>testing
<img src="crowds.jpg" title="Title" alt="alt text" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crowds and Earthquakes]]></title>
    <link href="http://ferenc-dv.github.io/atoms4peas/blog/2014/05/17/crowds-and-earthquakes/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-17T07:27:26-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ferenc-dv.github.io/atoms4peas/blog/2014/05/17/crowds-and-earthquakes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What do crowds, earthquakes, and water flow have in common? Push from linux at 11:20</p>

<p>=========</p>

<hr />

<h2>Crowd Disasters</h2>

<p>One of the important topics we would like to discuss in this blog is how ideas from complexity science become relevant to arms control and nonproliferation. Sometimes the relevance may not be immediately obvious to us but maybe it will in the future.</p>

<p>Take for example, the important problem of Crowd Disasters as discussed in the publication How to Save Human Lives with Complexity Science written by a multidisciplinary collaboration (Helbing <em>et al.</em>) from various institutes in Europe. This forward thinking [publication][1] was published on the arxiv.org preprint server (boy, do I feel old because I still think of it as the LANL preprint server) which after a decades of running is still a portal for new, innovative thinking. Crowd Disasters are events where people trample others often leading to many fatalities. The important point to remember is that these events are not caused because people deliberately want to hurt others. In fact, they are often not aware that they are harming anyone.</p>

<p>These horrific events are on the rise as venues become larger, and fatalities range from tens to as many as thousands of deaths per incident. The response to these events has often been through Crowd Control, the notion that these situations can be averted by controlling human behavior, which gives the impression that the problem is human behavior. If only it was possible to just modify human behavior then these problems would not occur. One of the important principles of disaster planning is base disaster planning on what people are likely to do not what they should do. An example of this I often think of is the case where a California city was warned that it would be a target of a tidal wave and city officials issued an order to evacuate the downtown and it was called a success because the entire downtown was cleared quickly. However, many of those who left went back to the beach to watch for the wave! However, as Helbing et al emphasize such views tend to blame the visitors of mass events, thereby preventing the proper understanding of crowd disasters and their avoidance in the future. In fact, there are misconceptions about the causes of these disasters that are only just now coming to light. An often stated cause for these disasters are mass panic which makes people behave in an irrational way and without regard to the welfare of others. In fact, it is well known that in emergencies people tend to behave quite rationally, as Erik Auf der Heide states in his important [Disaster Response][1]: &ldquo;Panic is not the typical response to disaster.&rdquo;</p>

<p>An often cited example of this is the 2005 Al-Aaimmah bridge stampede in Baghdad where rumors of an imminent suicide bomber attack apparently led to a stampede where as many as 953 people died. However, many of these types of events are not solely caused by mass panic stampedes as previously thought.</p>

<h2>Crowds of People as a Fluid</h2>

<p>To explain this further we need to think of a crowd of people moving as being similar to the flow of a fluid moving through a pipe, rather like water flowing from a tap. When one gently cracks open the water tap the water flows out smoothly. However, when the tap is opened more and more, the water will start to wonder back and forth and will behave erratically in an unpredictable way. This is known as the turbulent phase of fluid flow and is familiar to anyone who has flown or has sailed.</p>

<p>Helbing <em>et al</em>. recognized that similar instabilities happen in crowds as well. When the density of people increases past 2-4/m2 then the crowd starts to behave rather like what are known as phantom traffic jams. These are traffic jams that are produced because one person moves a little slower than the rest of traffic creating a shock wave slowing down all the drivers downstream who are trying to correct for the change in speed. In another <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0701203">publication</a>, Helbing, Johansson and Al-Abideen carefully studied videos taken of crowd motion during the annual pilgrimidge to the Hajj observed stop-and-go movement similar to that of phantom traffic jams but they do not seem to have the same cause. In fact, it seems that this type of flow behavior is expected based on the theory of granular flow near a bottleneck (see: <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0610151">D. Helbing et al, Analytical Approach to Continuous and Intermittent Bottleneck Flows, <em>Phys. Rev. Lett.</em>, 112, 068103, 2008</a>). These may be caused by competing interests to reach for a location away from the high densities and to reach an exit.  When the crowd reaches a critical density of 7/m2 (akin to the Reynolds number in fluid flow) the crowd exhibits a motion similar to turbulent flow. At this density the bodies cant help but touch and physical forces are transmitted from one person to the next a process which is unavoidable for the people bearing the forces. The forces can come from all directions and can form what Helbing et al call force chains, essentially shock waves which reverberate through the crowd.</p>

<blockquote><p>Don&rsquo;t believe me, see these mesmerizing videos of the Duisberg Love Parade incident where 21 people died because of crowd turbulence and ultimately improperly handling the crowd (<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xxd_KlaCiNY">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xxd_KlaCiNY</a>). See also the geo-tagged portal of videos related to this disaster at <a href="http://loveparadevideos.heroku.com/">http://loveparadevideos.heroku.com/</a>).`</p></blockquote>

<p>This is analogous to how earthquakes happen, in the sense that these are formed when layers of rock in a fault slip and stick abruptly when the forces on them overcomes the contact friction. The result is an unpredictable release of energy with displacements whose frequency follows a power law widely known as the Gutenberg-Richter law. In fact, when Helbing plots the distance between subsequent stops of crowd movement in the Hajj they find similar behavior in frequency as earthquakes do indicating self-similar behavior the focus of a future article in relation to the frequency of terrorist events.</p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/raw/master/src/common/images/icon48.png" title="Logo Title Text 1" alt="alt text" /></p>

<pre><code>Figure 1: Graph showing the power-law relationship for the frequency of earthquakes as a function of intensity and for the displacement of people in the crowd. Left graph taken from The Physics of Earthquakes by Hiroo Kanamori and Emily E Brodsky (Rep. Prog. Phys. 67 (2004) 14291496). The right graph extracted from Helbing et al, The Dynamics of Crowd Disasters: An Empirical Study, arXiv:physics/0701203v2.
</code></pre>

<p>The turbulent waves can produce such intense forces that the people in certain places are leaped great distances through the crowd. This is an artifact of the physics of fluid flow and has nothing to do with the mindset of the people involved in the incident. When the people in the crowd are pushed, they push against someone else and transmit the forces. What comes next, is more unfortunate physics, as these forces are transmitted through the crowd they can add up and it is only a matter of time until someone falls. This creates further unbalanced forces because now there is a region where the net forces come in a direction from which there is no opposing force keeping the person standing because the person in the direction of the force has fallen so that they are pushed from behind, but not anymore from the front, such that they are either forced to step on fallen persons (trampling) or they will also fall. This creates a domino effect where people near to the people who have fallen, fall as well, causing more people to be trampled. It is well known that people who are trampled, die of suffocation because of the weight of others on top of them prevents them from breathing.</p>

<h2>The Good News</h2>

<p>The good news is that Helbing et al have recognized that there are indicators that crowd turbulence may occur. For example, the onset of stop-and-go waves is a sign that the density is increasing to the point where crowd turbulence may happen. In this situation a pressure release measure must be taken to prevent the critical density from being reached. The authors also encourage better communication by organizers, security staff to issue instructions to the crowd and explain to them why they must wait when the passage ways are congested. The authors also stress the importance of maintaining good situational awareness and suggested using the GPS trackers on smartphones to facilitate this. They have started to investigate the potential of using smartphones for crowd management by implementing code in a program app for the largest festival in Switzerland which registers the location of participants at the festival. In the end, 28,000 participants voluntarily consented to anonymously contribute their location at the festival compared to 56,000 visitors that downloaded the app. Helbing and collaborators have produced maps where the density of people and the flow direction are displayed.</p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/raw/master/src/common/images/icon48.png" title="Logo Title Text 1" alt="alt text" /></p>

<pre><code>Figure 2: Figure taken from Helbing et al 2014.  Color-coded pedestrian speed before (left) during (middle) and after (right) the fireworks show.
</code></pre>

<p>It is still way early to predict the full potential of smartphones for crowd management but it clearly has a lot of possibilities as long as the data is properly managed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
